Finding aid for the Paul Monette papers, 1945-1995 LSC.1707
UCLA Library Special Collections
Paul Monette papers
1945-1995
UCLA Library Special Collections
Monette, Paul
LSC.1707
32.6 linear feet (64 document boxes, 7 flat boxes)
49 audiovisual carriers (1 film strip, 1 open reel videotape, 35 videocassettes, 12 audiocassettes)
21 born-digital carriers (16 floppy disks, 5 floppy discs)
Paul Landry Monette (1945-1995) was a novelist and poet. He received a best biography nomination from the National Book Critics' Circle and won the National Book Award for nonfiction in 1992. The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, proofs, notes, screenplays, plays, daybooks, memorabilia, photographs, clippings, and printed material related to Monette's life and literary career. Also included in the collection are the papers of two of Monette's significant others, Roger Horwitz and Stephen Kolzak.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Digital materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paul Monette, 1993-94.
Gift of Winston Wilde, 1996.
journals, 2012 addition
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9924702543606533
Biography
Paul Landry Monette was born in Lawrence, Massachusetts, on October 16, 1945; BA, English, Yale, 1967; taught at Cheshire Academy, Connecticut, 1968-70; taught at Milton Academy, Massachusetts, and Pine Manor College, 1970-76; met Roger Horwitz in 1974 and the two moved to Los Angeles, California, 1977; writings include Carpenter at the Asylum (1975), Taking Care of Mrs. Carroll (1978), The Gold Diggers (1979), Long Shot (1981), and No Witnesses (1981); after Horwitz's death in 1986, Monette wrote Love Alone: 18 Elegies for Rog (1988), Borrowed Time: an AIDS Memoir (1988), Afterlife (1990), and Halfway Home (1991); Monette's work, Borrowed Time: an AIDS Memoir, was nominated as best biography for the National Book Critics' Circle Award; Monette wrote of his struggle for identity as a gay man in his book, Becoming a Man: Half a Life Story (1992), which won the National Book Award for nonfiction in 1992; final publications include Last Watch of the Night (1994), West of Yesterday, East of Summer (1994), and the posthumous Sanctuary (1997); he died of complications from AIDS on February 10, 1995.
Biographical Note
Several printed obituaries and appreciations have been collected in Special Collections URL and can be found in the papers. Major critical overviews include those in Contemporary Authors: A Bio-Bibliographical Guide to Current Writers in Fiction, General Nonfiction, Poetry, Journalism, Drama, Motion Pictures, Television, and Other Fields vol. 139, edited by Donna Olendorf, Detroit, Washington, D.C., London: Gale Research Incorporated, 1993, Gay & Lesbian Literature, edited by Sharon Malinowski, Detroit and London: St. James Press, 1994, and Contemporary Gay American Novelists: A Bio-bibliographical Critical Sourcebook, edited by Emmanuel S. Nelson, Westport, Connecticut: Greenwod Press, 1994.
A Chronology of Paul Monette
By Paula Zeszotarski
Missing Title
October 16, 1945 Paul Landry Monette born in Lawrence, Massachusetts
1951 Brother Robert Monette born
1963 Graduated from Phillips Andover Academy
September 1963 Entered Yale University as a member of Jonathan Edwards College
Summer 1966 On scholarship to Cambridge University to work on senior thesis and travel in Europe
1967 Graduated from Yale University with Bachelor of Arts in English
September 1967-June 1968 Spent year on Carnegie Teaching Fellowship at Yale
November 1968-June 1970 Taught at Cheshire Academy, Cheshire, Connecticut
September 1970-1976 Taught at Milton Academy, Milton, Massachusetts and Pine Manor College and lived in Boston
September 4, 1974 Met Roger Horwitz
1975 Carpenter at the Asylum published
November 1977 Moved with Roger to Los Angeles
1978 First novel published, Taking Care of Mrs. Carroll
1979 Gold Diggers published
1981 Long Shot published
1981 No Witnesses published
1983 First novelization published, Scarface
November 29, 1984 Receives City of West Hollywood Certificate of Commendation
October 22, 1986 Roger Horwitz dies
1988 Love Alone: 18 Elegies for Rog published
1988 Borrowed Time published
1989 Borrowed Time nominated for National Book Critic's Circle Award
1990 Afterlife published
February 22, 1990 PM's mother dies
September 19 1990 Stephen Kolzak dies
1990(?) Met Winston Wilde
1991 Halfway Home published
1992 Becoming a Man published
1992* Won National Book [Critic's Circle] Award for Becoming a Man* the award was for 1992 but was given in 1993
June 1994 Last Watch of the Night published
July 1994 West of Yesterday, East of Summer published
February 10 1995 PM dies of complications from AIDS
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, proofs, notes, screenplays, plays, daybooks, memorabilia, photographs, clippings, and printed material related to the life and literary career of Paul Monette. Materials in the collection reflect Monette's childhood, education, relationships with significant others, writings, and public appearances. Correspondences in the collection include fan mail as well as letters from many prominent literary figures and gay and lesbian activist leaders. Daybooks document his life as a gay man in Los Angeles during the post-Stonewall rebellion and the beginning of the AIDS epidemic. Photographs document his receipt of the National Book Award in 1992, Monette's various friendships, and his home life with partners Roger Horwitz, Stephen Kolzak, and Winston Wilde. Portrait photographs include prints by Robert Giard, photographer of gay and lesbian authors. Also included in the collection are the papers of two of Monette's previous significant others, Roger Horwitz and Stephen Kolzak. The 2012 addition to the papers consists of 13 journals, dating from 1971-1992.
Expanded Scope and Content
These papers represent all those saved by Paul Monette and include documents relating to his childhood, education, significant others, writing career, activism, honors, and celebrity.
The papers contain a fairly complete sampling of manuscripts and publication materials including notes, rough drafts, typed drafts, and editor's and printer's copies of galley proofs. There are copies of his screenplays, television scripts, and plays. Notably, no complete manuscript of Taking Care of Mrs. Carroll or Becoming a Man appear in the papers (the latter was written and submitted on diskette); nor do the papers include a complete set of the literary journals that printed his poems. Monette provided copies of most of his books, including novelizations, and those are cataloged separately. (A copy of No Witnesses was not provided.)
Also found in the papers are clippings and copies of reviews and recordings of general speeches and appearances made for the publicity of particular published works. A substantial holding of fan mail has been filed in relationship to the published works in reference. There are manuscripts and notes pertaining to others' works, including some for which Monette wrote blurbs or prefaces, including A Rock and a Hard Place, by Anthony Godby Johnson. Records of Monette's poems set to music, primarily from Love Alone, can be found: composers include Ned Rorem, Roger Bourland, Jeffrey Brody, and Gary Bachlund.
Memorabilia, photographs, and daybooks cover his entire life. There are few snapshots of his childhood and adolescence. Some are interfiled in a baby book, but most primarily date to after his graduation from college. His home life with his partners Roger Horwitz, Stephen Kolzak, and Winston Wilde, and some friendships, particularly with Craig Rowland, Rudy Kikel, and Cesar Albini, are chronicled. There are few photographs from publicity tours, etcetera, that do not appear in publications. There are some photographs from his presentation at the Library of Congress after receiving the National Book Award in 1992. Portraits include prints by photographer Robert Giard, noteworthy photographer of gay and lesbian authors. Significantly, the papers hold all thirteen diaries Monette diligently kept from 1971 to 1992.
Correspondents represented in the papers include many prominent literary figures as well as gay and lesbian activist leaders, such as Louis Untermeyer, Richard Howard, Rudy Kikel, Joey Terrill, Elisabeth Nonas, Teresa DeCrecenzo, John Preston, Richard Labonté, Mark Thompson, Malcolm Boyd, Mark Thompson, Katherine V. Forrest, Betty Berzon, Torie Osborn, Michael Denneny, Doug Sadownick, Larry Duplechan, Gay Block, Malka Drucker, Guru Ma Jaya, Vito Russell, Alfred Corn, Philip Gambone, Eloise Klein Healy, David Groff, and Alison Bechdel. There are correspondences with fans, some of whom became friends--for example, Sascha Bittner. Condolences on the deaths of Roger Horwitz and Stephen Kolzak are extant. However, few outgoing correspondences exist in the papers, except for some photocopies of letters Monette evidently wished to save as well as letters he wrote to his parents during his first European tour that they, presumably, kept.
Also in Monette's papers are those of his two significant others who preceded him in death, Roger Horwitz and Stephen Kolzak. Those for Horwitz include records of his education, travel, and residence in France and friendship with Madeleine Follain, daughter of painter Maurice Denis. Horwitz's papers include poetry, diaries, correspondences, and documents pertaining to his post-Stonewall friendships with Craig Rowland and Rudy Kikel. Kolzak's records primarily consist of clippings and photographs; some relate to his work as casting director for the television series Cheers.
Organization and Arrangement
The Paul Monette papers are arranged in the following series and subseries:
Series 1: Journals
Series 2: Biographical
Subseries 2.1: Family and Friends
Subseries 2.2: Education and Teaching
Subseries 2.3: Relationships
Subseries 2.4: Press, Appearances, and Honors
Subseries 2.5: Projects, Involvements, etc.
Subseries 2.6: Personal Materials
Subseries 2.7: Memorial Items
Series 3: Biographical, Photographs
Series 4: Writings
Subseries 4.1: Poetry
Subseries 4.2: Fiction
Subseries 4.3: Screenplays/Television Scripts/Plays
Subseries 4.4: Nonfiction/Memoirs
Subseries 4.5: Fan Mail and Miscellaneous
Series 5: Roger Horwitz Papers
There was no filing order to the records as received. Paul Monette reviewed his papers and made some identifying notes and dates before giving them to the UCLA Library; he also reviewed a first draft finding aid to supply further dates (primarily of early poem manuscripts and publications), but he died before the processing was completed.
Materials are arranged largely chronologically. Accurate dates, however, were frequently difficult to determine. In the case of Monette's writings, the first publication or genesis of a work constituted the filing date for its related materials.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Paul Monette Papers (2 items).
Manuscripts for publication; Online resources.; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; AIDS (disease) in literature -- Archives.; Gay men's writings, American -- Archives.; Monette, Paul -- Archives; Horwitz, Roger; Kolzak, Stephen
- Series 1: Journals, 1971-1992
  Organization and Arrangement
  Series 1 has been arranged in chronological order.
  Scope and Content
  Series consists of 13 journals which provide details on Monette's personal life and professional career.
  - Journal One, 8 August 1971-5 December 1972; 152 pages; 19.5 x 25 cm (Box 58, Folder 1-2)
    In the first of his thirteen journals, dating from August 8, 1971 to December 5, 1972, Paul Monette records his thoughts on his sexuality, poetry, and various occupations.
    In the first half of the journal, Monette frequently expresses a wish to quit teaching literature on the high school level and become, instead, an interior decorator. Starting in Ipswich, as Monette completes his tenure as a theater instructor for Phillip Exeter Academy's summer programs, the journal subsequently documents Monette's second year as a literature instructor at Milton Academy. During this period, he regularly visits with friends and family in Boston, Milton, Andover, and Lawrence. He frequently worries that his previous bouts of pneumonia will return, that his loved ones will disapprove of his plan to launch an interior design business with his friend Mary (also referred to as "mvm"), and that a past affair he engaged in with a student named David while working at Cheshire Academy will continue to haunt him. The first half of the journal additionally documents two trips Monette takes to Houston with Mary—in hopes of garnering clients for their design business—as well as a trip he takes alone to Paris.
    Throughout the second half of the journal, Monette explores and discusses his sexuality at length. As his plans with Mary begin to fall apart, he seeks out therapy, wherein he works to suppress his feelings for a male student at Milton named Andy (also "AR") and strengthen a burgeoning relationship with a young woman named Julia Cameron (also "JBC"). At this time, Monette actively pursues sexual relationships with a number of women, chiefly his acquaintances Sally and Emily. He explicitly recounts a number of performance difficulties with them. Monette additionally records engaging sexually—despite his conviction not to—with a few men during this period. The first journal, it should be added, features prominently in his memoir Becoming a Man: Half a Life Story (1992), where he describes it as "so numbly unconscious, it takes [his] breath away to reread it today" (220). This fact might explain why some marginalia appears in the second half of the first journal, such as brackets marked in pencil. These brackets often correspond with passages Monette excerpts in Becoming a Man. On two occasions in the journal, brief marginal comments appear; both respond to his then sexual anxieties (pages 73 and 141 of the journal). The journal's second half also conveys an increasing sense of friction between Monette and his immediate family.
    Throughout, Monette expresses his thoughts on literature and his creative writing. He frequently discuses the writers and texts he teaches, especially the works of Wallace Stevens. He recounts a number of poetry readings he gives and attends. For example, he finds the poems that Adrienne Rich recites "embarrassing" (140). He discusses poems he is in the process of writing, many of which appear in his first volume of poetry. He intermittently quotes, without preface or commentary, passages from poets, playwrights, and philosophers, such as W. H. Auden and Henry Adams.
    The first journal contains a handful of notable features. A photograph of Monette is taped inside the front cover of the journal. Two items are taped inside the back cover: a piece of paper monogrammed with his and Julia's initials and what appears to be Monette's teaching schedule from the 1971-1972 school year. Two items are tucked into its back pages: a playbill from Monette's 1971 summer job as theater director at Exeter and two pages of typed journal entries. One of these typed entries replicates in full a hostile "fan" letter Monette wrote to Ezra Pound; this entry happens to be dated October 29, 1972, exactly three days before Pound's death.
  - Journal Two, 19 December 1972-16 February 1974; 144 pages; 20.5 x 27 cm (Box 58, Folder 3-4)
    In the second of his thirteen journals, dating from August 8, 1971 to December 5, 1972, Paul Monette documents his troubled feelings over his sexuality and chronicles significant developments in his literary career.
    Written for the most part in and around the Boston area, the second journal begins with Monette describing a complicated web of sexual encounters with his friends Sally (also referred to as "SJ"), Mary (also "mvm"), and Shannon (also "RFS"). Throughout the journal, Monette records his thoughts on what becomes a long-standing relationship with a young woman named Virginia (also "Ginny," "VA," or "V"), a short-lived but impassioned relationship with a young man named Pep Jensen (or, perhaps, "Pip"), and "cruising" at a local gay bar called "Sporter's." He notes socializing with Mary's gay male friends John and Roger (not Roger Horwitz, Monette's later partner) as well. With the expressed hopes of fostering a purely heterosexual identity, Monette visits regularly, the journal records, with a therapist named Rick Friswell (also "RF"—not to be confused with "RFS"). In some of his more distraught entries, Monette talks to—even curses at—himself as well as addresses Friswell and personifies his journal. On three occasions within the journal, Monette details sexually explicit and highly anxious dreams. Periodically, Monette identifies factors that he sees as contributing to his emotional fragility at this time. Some of these factors include surgery his mother undergoes to remove what turns out to be a benign tumor, a rash on his groin doctors determine to be Herpes, his often unactualized aspirations to quit smoking and exercise more frequently at the local YMCA, and the emerging Watergate scandal, which he and Virginia follow closely.
    At the same time, the second journal tracks developments in Monette's professional life and writing career. During this period, Monette works as a theatre teacher and director at Phillip Exeter Academy in the summers and as an English instructor at Milton Academy over the school years. The journal additionally describes Monette's struggle to get his and Mary's fledgling interior design business off the ground. His friendship with a gay couple, poet Richard Howard and novelist Sandy Friedman, who live in New York City, brings Monette in contact with literary elite. He mentions visiting with Anne Sexton, John Hollander, and James Merrill at their private residences, partaking in soirées at Frank Bidart's home, spending part of a day with Allen Ginsberg (whom he kisses on the cheek), frequenting poetry readings (most notably, those given by Randall Jarrell and Stanley Kunitz), and attending two high-profile funerals—for Jean Garrigue and Gordon Cairnie—where he brushes elbows with—respectively—Elizabeth Bishop and Adrienne Rich. The second journal records Monette's excitement when Little, Brown and Company accepts his manuscript—presumably his first book of poems, The Carpenter at the Asylum (1975)—for publication. Occasionally, Monette discusses the process of writing poems that eventually appear in his later poetry volume No Witnesses (1980), the poems "Degas" and "The Practice of Arrows" in particular.
    Throughout the journal, Monette comments on the literature he reads for pleasure. A list of the fiction he reads includes Murdoch's The Black Prince, Shulman's Memoirs of an Ex-Prom Queen, Conrad's The Secret Agent, Hellman's Pentimento, McHale's Principato, Bennett's Buried Alive, Updike's Of the Farm, and O'Connor's "The Artificial Nigger," as well as the works of John Cheever, Sarah Orne Jewett, Graham Greene, Marcel Proust, and Margery Allingham. A list of the nonfiction includes I'm OK, You're OK, Thoreau's Walden, Rilke's Letters to a Young Poet, Sackville-West's Portrait of a Marriage, Al Alvarez' criticism on Sylvia Plath, and W. H. Auden's essay on Alfred, Lord Tennyson. A list of the poetry includes the works of Robert Lowell, Ted Hughes, Edna St. Vincent Millay, Gerald Manley Hopkins, John Berryman, Malcolm Cowley, and Sappho. Similarly, Monette discusses at times the literary works he teaches, such as King Lear, Paradise Lost (and "Lycidas"), The Great Gatsby, The Country Wife, and Spark's Memento Mori, as well as those of Hart Crane, Anne Bradstreet, Chaucer, Robert Frost, W. D. Snodgrass, Richard Wilbur, and Jorge Luis Borges.
    Finally, the second journal contains a number of notable features. A business card from "Sandpiper Beach House" in Provincetown and a photograph of Monette (that he describes on page 103) are taped inside the journal's front cover. Taped inside its back cover is a photograph of Monette. A handwritten note from a friend (most likely Virginia) is tucked into the front of the journal. Taped to the front flyleaf is a clasped envelop containing eight distinct items: two schedules handwritten on loose-leaf notebook pages; a magazine clipping; two notes from friends (from Virginia and a woman named Wendy); two typed playbills from his stints as Exeter's summer theatre director; and one loose-leaf journal entry. Within the journal, Monette diagrams the floorplans of three apartments, including James Merrill's in Stonington, CT.
  - Journal Three, 23 Februrary 1974-13 May 1975; 300 pages; 20 x 25 cm (Box 58, Folder 5)
    In the third of his thirteen journals, dating from February 23, 1974 to May 13, 1975, Paul Monette expresses his thoughts on the books he reads, the poems he writes, and the literature he teaches. He also describes meeting and dating Roger Horwitz, his partner of twelve years.
    The third journal begins with Monette considering new ways to structure his entries, desiring a more impressionistic and less narrative form than in the two previous journals. Throughout, he recounts trips to Dartmouth, Sea Island, GA, New Haven, CT, New York City, and Provincetown, MA. He describes ongoing quarrels with old friends (primarily Sally, or "SJ," and Shannon, or "RSF"), his desire to quit smoking cigarettes, eat healthier, and reduce his dependence on "dope," and his therapy sessions with Rick Friswell (or "RF"). He also expresses pleasure at reconnecting with two men named Sandy—"Sandy F," the novelist Sanford Friedman, and "Sandy," the writer J. D. McClatchy—and commencing a romantic relationship with the former. A third of the way through the journal, on September 2, 1974, Monette marks the occasion of meeting his future life partner by simply writing, "Roger Horwitz." The brevity of the entry anticipates Monette's later rendering of the occasion near the end of his memoir Becoming a Man: Half a Life Story (1992): "Roger Horwitz, Paul Monette. Say hello to the rest of your life" (276). From that point on, the journal primarily focuses on their fledging relationship as well as Monette's struggle to choose definitively between Roger and Sandy F. The third journal also conveys a sense of Monette's eventually life-long fascination with Henry David Thoreau and Walden Pond, where—as the third journal records—he frequently reads, sunbathes, and skinny dips. As in previous journals, Monette remarks on a number of his encounters with literary elite such as James Merrill, Frank Bidart, Helen Vendler, and Harold Bloom (who was Monette's undergraduate thesis advisor). Periodically, Monette describes highly sexual dreams that trouble him, the process of composing his poems, the daily grind of instructing literature classes at Milton Academy, and visits with his immediate family. In these passages, Monette analyzes his mother's behavior through an explicitly and self-consciously Freudian lens. He occasionally notes, as well, positive advances in his poetry career. The final entry, for instance, records Monette receiving the first hardcopy of his first volume of poems, The Carpenter at the Asylum (1975), in the mail.